{"tossups": [{"question": "After the death of his horse, one character in a work named after this man decides to throw a cannon into the sea, only to find out that a wizard has brought it back to use. A character in that work named after this person forgets about his love while trapped in an island due to the sorcery of Alcina. The last line of a poem named for this character declares that the story was brought by a legendary poet named Turodolus. In a work named for this man, (*) Thierry defeats Pinabel in a duel shortly before the traitorous Ganelon is teared apart by horses. In that work, this character\u2019s temples burst while blowing an oliphaunt horn before dying at Roncevaux Pass. For 10 points, name this nephew of Charlamagne, the subject of a namesake Chanson.", "answer": "Roland (or Orlando; accept Song of Roland or La Chanson de Roland; accept Orlando Furioso)", "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Roland</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Roland"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or Orlando; accept Song of Roland or La Chanson de Roland; accept Orlando Furioso"}, {"question": "A work by this author opens with a character poking coals on a grate; that character later quotes a definition of life as a \u201ccombination of heterogeneous changes.\u201d The metal worker Haley appears in that work, whose title character is noticed for wearing a red fez hat. In another work by this author, the protagonist hears \u201cwhispers in an unknown tongue\u201d and wind in the trees making the music of Aeolian harps. A (*) \u201cgrey clad\u201d soldier tricks one of this writer\u2019s protagonists,who later realizes that a sound \u201clike the stroke of a blacksmith\u2019s hammer upon the anvil\u201d came from his own pocket watch. This creator of the title chess-playing robot in the story \u201cMoxon\u2019s Master\u201d also wrote about Peyton Farquhar\u2019s seeking to burn down the title structure before being hanged by Union soldiers. For 10 points, name this author of \u201cAn Occurrence at Owl Creek Bridge.\u201d", "answer": "Ambrose Bierce", "subcategory": "Short Fiction", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Ambrose <b><u>Bierce</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Ambrose Bierce"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The protagonist of one novel by this author secretly meets friends such as Steve Hart and Joe Bryne in the hills and later falls in love with an Irish girl named Mary. While on a trip near the Bellingen River, characters in another novel by this author watch Mr. Jeffris brutally murder a native man. One character in that novel by this author meets his friend Wardley-Fish and marries Miriam Chadwick after the central action is completed. Thomas Curnow betrays a character created by this author during a brawl at Glenrowan. Another novel by this author involves two characters making a (*) bet regarding the transportation of a Glass Church to Boat Harbour, requiring traversal through the Outback. For 10 points, name this Australian author of The True History of the Kelly Gang and Oscar and Lucinda.", "answer": "Peter Carey", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Peter <b><u>Carey</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Peter Carey"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The protagonist of one story by this author repeatedly describes his love for another character, who responds with \u201cah, ah.\u201d In one story by this author, a character tells the protagonist about Pirlipat\u2019s transformation into an ugly figure. Olympia is revealed to not be the daughter of Spallanzi and instead an automaton created by (*) Coppelius in one story by this author. In that story by this author, Clara is saved by Lothar from falling off a tall steeple, which Nathanael jumps from after shouting \u201cpretty eyes, pretty eyes.\u201d The clockmaker Drosselmeyer gives Marie the title object in a story by this author which was adapted into a Tchaikovsky ballet. For 10 points, name this German author of \u201cThe Sandman\u201d and \u201cThe Nutcracker and the Mouse King.\u201d", "answer": "E.T.A. Hoffman [or Ernst Theodor Amadeus Hoffmann]", "subcategory": "Short Fiction", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "E.T.A. <b><u>Hoffman</u></b> [or <b><u>Ernst Theodor Amadeus Hoffmann</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["E.T.A. Hoffman", "Ernst Theodor Amadeus Hoffmann"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Description acceptable. As a result of one of these things, a character\u2019s mother is blinded by her baby daughter at birth. That character has her face cut by her aunt and turns into a beggar as a result of one of these things. One character has two names as a result of one of these things, which allows them to change sex by immersing themselves in water. The most notable one of these is lost as a result of a (*) medical operation, and a character uses one of these to say \u201call this is pointless\u2014they\u2019ll finish us before we start!\u201d at a meeting with a group of people who have these things. The main character of the work in which these things appear is switched at birth with a boy whose one of these things gives him the nickname \u201cShiva of the Knees.\u201d For 10 points, name these supernatural traits possessed by children born within an hour of India\u2019s independence in a Salman Rushdie novel.", "answer": "the powers of the Midnight\u2019s Children [accept equivalents; prompt on just \u201cMidnight\u2019s Children\u201d with \u201cWhat do they have?\u201d]", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>the powers of the Midnight\u2019s Children</u></b> [ accept equivalents; prompt on <u>just \u201cMidnight\u2019s Children\u201d with \u201cWhat do they have?\u201d</u>]", "acceptable": ["the powers of the Midnight\u2019s Children"], "promptable": ["just \u201cMidnight\u2019s Children\u201d with \u201cWhat do they have?\u201d"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a poem by this author, the title figure tries to relieve her guilt by talking to \u201cdim killed children\u201d but only succeeds in saying \u201cI loved you all.\u201d The central figures of another poem by this author live in a \u201crented back room\u201d filled with \u201ctobacco crumbs, vases, and fringes.\u201d A poem by this author opens \u201cAbortions will not let you forget.\u201d Another poem by this author describes \u201cdinner as a (*) casual affair\u201d for the \u201cold yellow pair\u201d that eat the title food. Another poem by this author sees the central characters \u201cstrike straight\u201d and \u201clurk late.\u201d This poet wrote about seven pool players at the Golden Shovel who \u201csing sin\u201d and \u201cdie soon.\u201d For 10 points, name this first African-American to win a Pulitzer Prize, the author of \u201cthe mother,\u201d \u201cThe Bean Eaters,\u201d and \u201cWe Real Cool.\u201d", "answer": "Gwendolyn Brooks", "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Gwendolyn <b><u>Brooks</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Gwendolyn Brooks"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This character is pronounced dead after escaping from a ship by falling off of its rigging. \u201cHe died when he no longer had his angel\u201d is engraved on this character\u2019s unmarked grave. This character uses a file hidden in a coin to escape from ropes after fearing that a man is hiding in his garden. This man saves Champmathieu\u2019s life before calling a man \u201cthe Emperor.\u201d This character moves out of a convent owned by Fauchelevent, whom he saved by pulling a (*) carriage cart off of him. This character\u2019s soul is \u201cbought\u201d by Bishop Myriel for two silver candlesticks before he becomes mayor of Montreuil-sur-Mer under the name Monsieur Madeleine. For 10 points, name this character who adopts Cosette and is pursued by Inspector Javert in Victor Hugo\u2019s Les Miserables.", "answer": "Jean Valjean [accept either; accept Monsieur Madeleine until read]", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Jean Valjean</u></b> [accept <b><u>either</u></b>; accept <b><u>Monsieur Madeleine until read</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Jean Valjean", "either", "Monsieur Madeleine until read"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A character in one of this author\u2019s novels angers his father by writing a scholarly article on Charles Darwin. A poet is replaced by a radio in a novel by this author, which ends with a barber who joined the British army being beaten to death by a group of British soldiers after smashing a glass of beer in a prostitute\u2019s face. That novel by this author includes an untrained dentist who sells fake teeth he stole from dead bodies, Dr. (*) Booshy. This man also wrote a novel in which a boy sees his father, who had previously banned music, playing a tambourine. Amina is hit by a car and Yasin has an affair with a courtesan in that novel by this author, which is part of a trilogy containing Palace Walk and Sugar Street. For 10 points, name this Egyptian author of Midaq Alley and the Cairo Trilogy.", "answer": "Naguib Mahfouz", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Naguib <b><u>Mahfouz</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Naguib Mahfouz"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One of these animals created by Mary Chase is described as \u201c6 foot and 3 and one-half inches tall'' by Elwood P. Dowd, whose sister\u2019s purse was hidden by that imaginary animal after he was booked into a sanitarium. Another one of these animals is the main character of Joel Chandler Harris\u2019 Uncle Remus stories and frequently runs into problems in The Laughin\u2019 Place. In one story, a group of these animals get help from a bird named (*) Kehaar and are attacked at the title location. The daughter of a character nicknamed after this animal drowns in a bathtub; that character, Harry Angstrom, is a former high school basketball star created by John Updike. For 10 points, name these mammals, the central characters in Harvey and Watership Down.", "answer": "rabbits [do not accept or prompt on hares; accept Pooka due to some ambiguity regarding Harvey]", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>rabbits</u></b> [do not accept or prompt on \"hares\"; accept <b><u>Pooka due to some ambiguity regarding Harvey</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["rabbits", "Pooka due to some ambiguity regarding Harvey"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": ["hares"], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This character criticizes his surroundings when he first appears, and his request for a certain accomodation is taken as evidence for his \u201csense of human dignity.\u201d When someone asks this character if he has a pocket-mirror, he covers his face with his hands, believing that he could last \"ten thousand years with only [his] thoughts for company.\" Another character disturbs this character because he cannot (*) blink. This character, who planned to publish a pacifist newspaper in Mexico, becomes distraught when his colleagues deride him for deserting the military. This character stays with two companions in hopes of convincing them that he is not a coward; those characters are Inez and Estelle. For 10 points, what character exclaims, \"Hell is other people!\" in No Exit by Jean-Paul Sartre?", "answer": "Joseph Garcin [accept either]", "subcategory": "Drama", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Joseph Garcin</u></b> [accept <b><u>either</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Joseph Garcin", "either"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Description Acceptable. The beginning of a work made up of these texts recounts the protagonist getting beat up for supposedly \u201cwinking\u201d at a boy at church. One of these texts mentions Miss Millie calling a character\u2019s actions \u201cungrateful\u201d and is present alongside another of these texts which describes the Olinka tribe. One of these \u201cchapters\u201d describes a reunion at a July barbeque, while another describes a quilt being torn apart. A depiction of (*) Corrine falling ill is present in one of these texts, another of which describes the protagonist\u2019s pursuit of a woman towards Memphis, Tennessee. Many of these texts describe a character\u2019s rape and abuse by Alphonso, while some describe their writer\u2019s affair with the blues singer Shug Avery. For 10 points, name these epistles that make up an Alice Walker novel.", "answer": "letters in The Color Purple [prompt on letters; accept Celie\u2019s letters or Nettie\u2019s letters; accept synonyms for letters; accept chapters, portions, or anything of that nature in The Color Purple until \u201cchapters\u201d is read]", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>letters in The Color Purple</u></b> [prompt on <u>letters</u>; accept <b><u>Celie\u2019s letters</u></b> or <b><u>Nettie\u2019s letters</u></b>; accept <b><u>synonyms for letters</u></b>; accept <b><u>chapters, portions,</u></b> or <b><u>anything of that nature in The Color Purple until \u201cchapters\u201d is read</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["letters in The Color Purple", "Celie\u2019s letters", "Nettie\u2019s letters", "synonyms for letters", "chapters, portions,", "anything of that nature in The Color Purple until \u201cchapters\u201d is read"], "promptable": ["letters"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One source claims that a draft of this poem was written on a folded piece of paper containing notes on Empedocles. That draft\u2019s last line described \u201cnaked shingles of the world.\u201d A character in a work based on this poem explains \u201cthings are bad / All over,\u201d and that work\u2019s title figure thinks about \u201cenormous beds\u201d and \u201cblandishments in French.\u201d This poem describes \u201cvast edges drear\u201d and a \u201cmoon-blanched land\u201d that is \u201cso various\u201d and \u201cso new.\u201d This poem says that one figure heard the (*) \u201ceternal note of sadness\u2026 long ago\u201d on the Aegean Sea. The title figure is given a \u201cbottle of Nuit d\u2019Amour\u201d in a parody of this poem by Anthony Hecht. This poem describes a \u201cmelancholy, long, withdrawing roar\u201d and a \u201cdarkling plain\u201d where \u201cignorant armies clash by night.\u201d For 10 points, name this Matthew Arnold poem written about the cliffs of England.", "answer": "\u201cDover Beach\u201d", "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>\u201cDover Beach\u201d</u></b>", "acceptable": ["\u201cDover Beach\u201d"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "While living in Capri, this author coined the term \u201cGod building,\" which incorporates \u201creligious atheism\u201d for collective humanity. In a poem by this author, the \u201cblack Demon of the tempest\u201d scares groups of birds before the title bird cries \u201cLet it break in all its fury!\" In a short story by this author, after a 16-year old girl is seduced by a soldier, she is threatened by a group of men who had given her kringles every morning. In a play by this author, a character remarks \"You spoiled the song, you idiot,\u201d after the (*) Actor commits suicide. In that play by this author of \u201cThe Song of the Stormy Petrel\u201d and \u201cTwenty Six Men and a Girl,\" boiling water is poured on Natasha\u2019s feet, setting off a brawl in which Vaska murders his landlord Kostilyoff. For 10 points, name this Russian author of The Lower Depths.", "answer": "Maxim Gorky [or Alexei Maximovich Peshkov]", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Maxim <b><u>Gorky</u></b> [or <b><u>Alexei Maximovich Peshkov</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Maxim Gorky", "Alexei Maximovich Peshkov"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The protagonist of this novel broke her legs in two places skiing down a hill. The protagonist reads a story about a Jew falling in love with a nun in this novel, later comparing the story to her hatred for a character who slept with the maid Gladys. Marco demands his diamond pin back after attempting to rape this novel\u2019s protagonist, who flirts with a sailor and tells him that her name is (*) Elly Higginbottom. After hemorrhaging upon losing her virginity to Irwin, this novel\u2019s protagonist is taken to the hospital by Joan, who later hangs herself. The medical student Buddy Willard is the former love interest of the protagonist in this novel, which begins with her pondering the execution of the Rosenbergs. Dr. Gordon administers electroshock treatment to the protagonist of, for 10 points, what novel about Esther Greenwood\u2019s depression, written by Sylvia Plath?", "answer": "The Bell Jar", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>The Bell Jar</u></b>", "acceptable": ["The Bell Jar"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A character in this play rebuffs another\u2019s compliments by claiming that she has \u201csomething of the Puritan in me.\u201d An Australian businessman in this play is in love with a character who only says \u201cYes mamma.\u201d This play\u2019s protagonist\u2019s husband owns a checkbook with a lock on it, which she breaks to discover payments to another woman. A character in this play comments \u201cWe are all in the (*) gutter, but some of us are looking at the stars.\u201d The protagonist overhears Cecil Graham's comments about the nature of women as she hides behind a curtain in this play. A character requests a photo of the protagonist and her son as she leaves to marry Lord Augustus at the end of this play, earlier claiming ownership of the title object left on a table at Lord Darlington\u2019s house. Mrs. Erlynne never reveals that she is the title character\u2019s mother in, for 10 points, what Oscar Wilde play?", "answer": "Lady Windermere\u2019s Fan", "subcategory": "Drama", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Lady Windermere\u2019s Fan</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Lady Windermere\u2019s Fan"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A line from this poem titles Elyn Saks\u2019 autobiography, which describes her experiences living with schizophrenia. A concept described in this poem is \u201cvexed to nightmare.\" A certain image \u201ctroubles [the speaker\u2019s] sight\u201d in this poem, which describes \u201cA gaze blank\u2026 as the sun\u201d and \u201cshadows of\u2026 desert (*) birds.\" This poem, which claims that a \u201cceremony of innocence is drowned,\" decries those \u201cfull of passionate intensity.\u201d This poem describes a \u201cblood-dimmed tide\u201d and mentions the \u201cSpiritus Mundi\u201d before describing a \u201crough beast\u2026 moving its slow thighs.\" A line from this poem was used to title Chinua Achebe\u2019s first novel and states \u201cThings fall apart; the center cannot hold.\" For 10 points, name this W. B. Yeats poem that references the return of Christ.", "answer": "\u201cThe Second Coming\u201d", "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>\u201cThe Second Coming\u201d</u></b>", "acceptable": ["\u201cThe Second Coming\u201d"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One man locks this character in a crucible to distill him and regain some pills this character had consumed. This character releases the Cloud Horses after realizing he was given a low status, \u201cProtector of the Horses.\u201d After being tricked to put a circlet on his head, this character can be controlled by another through headache spells. This character urinates on five (*) stone pillars before realizing that they are the hand of another character. This character is forced by a priest to accompany him to Vulture Peak along with Sandy and Pig. This character has a staff that can enlarge and contract at his will. This character rebels against heaven but is trapped under a mountain by the Buddha until he is freed by the monk Tang Sanzang. For 10 points, name this \u201cMonkey King,\u201d a central character in Journey to the West.", "answer": "Sun Wukong [accept Monkey King before read; prompt on partial answers]", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Sun Wukong</u></b> [accept <b><u>Monkey King</u></b> before read; prompt on <u>partial answers</u>]", "acceptable": ["Sun Wukong", "Monkey King"], "promptable": ["partial answers"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In this play, Willie proclaims that he was accepted at Harvard with the same cordiality that Longfellow would have shown to a black woman dancing on Brittle Street. Two characters in this play joke about how they could\u2019ve killed each other in the Boer War. One character remarks \u201c\u2019tis cool beneath thy willow trees\u201d after stating that \u201cthe days grow hot, O Babylon.\u201d A character in this play walks outside after (*) twenty years but comes back indoors after supposedly dodging an automobile. Guilt-ridden for turning in his mother who led \u201cthe Movement,\u201d Don Parritt throws himself off the fire escape at the end of this play. In this play, Hickey admonishes other people about following \u201cpipe dreams\u201d before admitting to killing his wife. For 10 points, name this play about people residing in Harry Hope\u2019s saloon, a work by Eugene O\u2019Neill.", "answer": "The Iceman Cometh", "subcategory": "Drama", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>The Iceman Cometh</u></b>", "acceptable": ["The Iceman Cometh"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This character asks another whether a madman \u201cbe a gentleman or a yeoman\u201d before mocking those who trust in the \u201ctameness of a wolf.\u201d This character describes a time \u201cwhere nobles are their tailors\u2019 tutors'' as part of a \u201cprophecy Merlin shall make.\u201d His superior comments \u201cI think the world\u2019s asleep\u201d while asking for this character. This character\u2019s last line before his unexplained disappearance is \u201cAnd I\u2019ll go to bed at noon\u201d in response to a remark about \u201csupper i\u2019 th\u2019 morning.\u201d He frequently debates with his master, whom he addresses as (*) \u201cnuncle.\u201d This character mistakes Tom O\u2019Bedlam for a spirit and accompanies a monarch into a raging storm. For 10 points, name this coxcomb wearing character who often provides comic relief in Shakespeare\u2019s King Lear.", "answer": "King Lear\u2019s Fool", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>King Lear\u2019s Fool</u></b>", "acceptable": ["King Lear\u2019s Fool"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One of this author's early poems describes a bird that flies off from \u201ca withered branch.\u201d In another poem, this author depicts the penetrating power of a cicada's screech. This author frequently included motifs of changing weather, including one that portrays \u201cfishes' eyes\u201d that are \u201cwith tears\u201d at the end of spring. In this author's first publication, a referee compares two poems side-by-side, including two written by himself. That collection's name references a children's game of placing two (*) shells side-by-side to compare them. A water sound often translated as \u201cKerplunk\u201d or \u201cSplash\u201d results when a frog leaps into an old pond in another work by this author. For 10 points, what author wrote a collection of 17-syllable haiku in The Narrow Road to the Deep North?", "answer": "Matsuo Basho [accept either]", "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Matsuo <b><u>Basho</u></b> [accept <b><u>either</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Matsuo Basho", "either"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}